<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</origin><title>John H. Chafee Coastal Barrier Resources System Approximate Polygons</title><geoform>vector digital data</geoform><pubdate>20100401</pubdate><pubinfo><pubplace>Arlington, VA</pubplace><publish>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</publish></pubinfo></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This Coastal Barrier Resources System (CBRS) data set, produced by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (Service), contains areas designated as undeveloped coastal barriers in accordance with the Coastal Barrier Resources Act (CBRA), 16 U.S.C. 3501 et seq., as amended. The boundaries used to create the polygons herein were initially compiled between 4/1/2007 and 4/1/2010 from the official John H. Chafee Coastal Barrier Resources System CBRS maps. The majority of the boundaries were digitized from the official paper maps. In cases where the official map was created through digital methods, the digital boundary was used. As maps are revised this data set will be updated with the new boundaries. This data set contains CBRS polygons that have varying levels of horizontal accuracy depending on the methods used for digitization of the boundaries, and the age and quality of the official CBRS map. The different levels of horizontal accuracy are described below in the horizontal accuracy statement. These digital polygons are only representations of the CBRS boundaries shown on the official CBRS maps and are not to be considered authoritative. The Service is not responsible for any misuse or misinterpretation of this digital data set, including use of the data to determine eligibility for federal financial assistance such as federal flood insurance.CBRS maps are either enacted by Congress or adopted administratively by the Secretary of the Interior (Secretary), and are maintained by the Service. Copies of the official CBRS maps are available for viewing at Service’s Headquarters office and are also available to view or download at http://www.fws.gov/cbra/maps. CBRS boundaries viewed using the CBRS Mapper or the shapefile are subject to misrepresentations beyond the Service’s control, including misalignments of the boundaries with third party base layers and misprojections of spatial data. The official CBRS map is the controlling document and should be consulted for all official determinations. Official determinations are recommended for all properties that are in close proximity (within about 150 feet) of a CBRS boundary. For an official determination of whether or not an area or specific property is located within the CBRS, please follow the procedures found at http://www.fws.gov/cbra/determinations.html. For any questions regarding the CBRS, please contact your local Service field office or email CBRA@fws.gov. Contact information for Service field offices can be found at http://www.fws.gov/offices.</abstract><purpose>This data set was created to provide local users with a general depiction of the aerial extent of the boundaries of the John H. Chafee Coastal Barrier Resources System.</purpose></descript><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>As needed</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-97.637708</westbc><eastbc>-64.623139</eastbc><northbc>47.435609</northbc><southbc>17.671676</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>None</themekt><themekey>CBRS</themekey><themekey>Coastal Barrier Resources System</themekey><themekey>John H. Chafee</themekey><themekey>CBRS Unit</themekey><themekey>Coastal Barrier</themekey><themekey>Flood Insurance Prohibition</themekey><themekey>CBRA</themekey><themekey>Otherwise Protected Area</themekey><themekey>CBIA</themekey><themekey>Coastal Barrier Resources Act</themekey><themekey>Coastal Barrier Improvement Act</themekey><themekey>OPA</themekey></theme><place><placekt>None</placekt><placekey>Minnesota</placekey><placekey>Wisconsin</placekey><placekey>Michigan</placekey><placekey>Ohio</placekey><placekey>New York</placekey><placekey>Maine</placekey><placekey>Massachusetts</placekey><placekey>Rhode Island</placekey><placekey>Connecticut</placekey><placekey>New Jersey</placekey><placekey>Delaware</placekey><placekey>Maryland</placekey><placekey>Virginia</placekey><placekey>North Carolina</placekey><placekey>South Carolina</placekey><placekey>Georgia</placekey><placekey>Florida</placekey><placekey>Alabama</placekey><placekey>Mississippi</placekey><placekey>Louisiana</placekey><placekey>Texas</placekey><placekey>United States Virgin Islands</placekey><placekey>Puerto Rico</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>User must read and fully comprehend the metadata prior to data use. User must acknowledge the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service as the originator when using the data set as a source. User must share data products developed using this source data set with the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service. Data should not be used beyond the limits of the source scale. The data set is NOT a survey document and should not be utilized as such. The data set is NOT to be used for definitive in/out determinations.</useconst><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</cntorg><cntper>Katie Niemi</cntper></cntorgp><cntpos>National Coastal Barriers Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing address</addrtype><address>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</address><address>4401 N. Fairfax Drive, Suite 840</address><city>Arlington</city><state>VA</state><postal>22203</postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>703-358-2161</cntvoice><cntemail>CBRA@fws.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac><timeperd><timeinfo><rngdates><begdate>19901024</begdate><enddate>20081015</enddate></rngdates></timeinfo><current>publication date</current></timeperd></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>Independent quality control checks were conducted on all attributes.</attraccr></attracc><logic>Topological checks were conducted to ensure that no polygons overlap and that adjacent boundaries are coincident where appropriate.</logic><complete>In most cases the seaward boundary of a CBRS unit is defined by the 30 foot bathymetric contour rather than a hard boundary depicted on the official source map. In these cases, the digital boundaries have been terminated by connecting the ends of the lateral boundaries on the seaward side. Therefore, the actual CBRS seaward boundary may extend farther offshore than is shown by the polygons.  In large coastal embayments and the Great Lakes, the boundary is defined by the 20-ft bathymetric contour or a line approximately one mile seaward of the shoreline, whichever is nearer the coastal barrier.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>The CBRS polygons in this data set have two tiers of horizontal accuracy depending on the methods used for digitization of the boundaries, and the age and quality of the official CBRS map.  Tier 1 polygons are of lower quality and accuracy than Tier 2 polygons.  As the Service modernizes the CBRS maps, Tier 1 polygons will be upgraded to Tier 2.  Tier 1:  Centerline Boundaries:  Polygons attributed with a Tier 1 accuracy level were created by digitizing the center of the CBRS boundaries shown on the official paper maps (mostly published in 1990).  The potential sources of error are described below. Base map accuracy:  Most of the official CBRS maps use United States Geological Survey (USGS) Quadrangles (quads) as a base map.  USGS quads are tested to meet the National Map Accuracy Standards, and have a declared horizontal accuracy of at least 90% at the “well-defined points” tested, with an error of approximately plus or minus 40 feet.  However, the majority of the boundaries used to create the Tier 1 polygons follow several categories of features shown on the quads (such as vegetative breaks, shorelines, and mangrove stands) that cannot be considered to be “well-defined points,” and therefore may have a greater degree of horizontal error than is stated above.  As such, the CBRS boundaries on the official maps will have inherited the level of error in horizontal accuracy of the quads. Georeferencing accuracy:  Additional error may have been introduced during the georeferencing process.  Generally, the paper CBRS maps were scanned and then georeferenced to a USGS or third party Digital Raster Graphic (DRG) of the quad covering the same area as the CBRS map.  Therefore, any horizontal error in the DRG can be assumed to have been inherited during the georeferencing process.  The Service makes no claim to the accuracy of third party data used in this process.  Furthermore, new error could have been introduced during the georeferencing process as a result of inexact or insufficient control point selection.  However, all georeferenced maps were visually inspected for adequate fit to the DRG and aerial imagery along the boundary.   Digitization of the boundary:  Every attempt was made to digitize the exact center of the boundaries on the official CBRS maps.  However, because the boundary lines on these maps vary in width between 80 and 100 feet on the ground and the boundaries appear pixilated at the scale used in the digitization process, it was difficult to consistently define the centerline of the CBRS boundaries.  Therefore, additional error was introduced as a result of this process. Gaps in boundaries:  The official CBRS maps occasionally have gaps in the boundary where no line was drawn to avoid obscuring a feature label on the quad.  In these places, cartographic judgment was used and the boundary was digitized generally to follow the feature that the boundary was following on the DRG, or drawn as a straight line if the boundary intent was not clear. Edge matching:  Many CBRS units extend across multiple maps.  In some cases there are significant disjunctions between the boundaries at the edges of adjacent maps because of the manual process that was used to draw the CBRS boundaries.  Cartographic judgment was used to determine the best way to eliminate these disjunctions on a case by case basis.  Additionally, many of the official CBRS maps were created by physically cutting paper quads and taping them together (splicing) to achieve the desired map extent prior to drawing the boundaries.  In almost every case there was some error introduced by imperfect edge matching.  Poor splices on the official CBRS maps were accounted for by georeferencing the maps multiple times.  For example, in cases where the official CBRS map was composed of two different quads taped together vertically down the middle, the western half of the map would be georeferenced and digitized separately from the eastern half.  This typically resulted in a disjunction where the CBRS boundary on either side of the splice comes together.  In these cases, cartographic judgment was used to determine the best way to eliminate disjunctions.  Tier 2:  Digital Conversion and Comprehensively Modernized Boundaries: The Service has two ongoing map modernization projects:  (1) digital conversion, which produces modernized maps that have very limited changes and can be adopted administratively (changes limited to those authorized under 16 U.S.C. 3503(c)-(e)); and (2) comprehensive map modernization, which produces comprehensively revised maps that contain more significant changes and must be enacted by Congress to become effective (mandated by Sections 3 and 4 of P.L. 109-226).  For more information about CBRA mapping, visit http://www.fws.gov/cbra. Polygons attributed with a Tier 2 accuracy level were created with modern Geographic Information Systems (GIS) technology using orthorectified aerial imagery (orthoimagery) as the base map.  Because CBRS boundaries are often tied to features visible on the base map, the CBRS boundaries with Tier 2 accuracy are most reliable when paired with the base image that they were digitized on and are much higher quality than Tier 1 boundaries.  To obtain the source of the base map image for a particular map, please email CBRA@fws.gov.  Since 1999, Tier 2 boundaries have been used to create paper maps that were either enacted into law by Congress or administratively adopted by the Secretary.  A potential source of error is described below. Spatial accuracy of orthoimagery:  The orthoimagery is obtained from multiple sources and is selected based on quality, cost, and coverage availability.  The imagery selected for use in this process must have met the following guidelines:  it must be no more than two years old at the time of boundary digitization, it must have a resolution of 1 meter pixels or less, and the imagery must be orthorectified.  Commonly used orthoimagery for Tier 2 boundaries is from the National Agriculture Imagery Program (NAIP).  NAIP imagery has an accuracy of +/- 20 feet.  Many CBRS boundaries are drawn to have specific relationships to features shown on the orthoimage that they were digitized on.  Therefore, the CBRS boundaries inherit the spatial accuracy of base orthoimagery, and may appear not to fit other images properly.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><lineage><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</origin><title>Official CBRS source maps</title><geoform>map</geoform></citeinfo></srccite><srcscale>1: 24,000 and 1:25,000</srcscale><typesrc>Digital file and hard copy paper</typesrc><srccitea>CBRS source maps</srccitea><srccontr>Location of CBRS boundaries</srccontr></srcinfo></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><direct>Vector</direct><ptvctinf><sdtsterm><sdtstype>GT-polygon composed of chains</sdtstype><ptvctcnt>1013</ptvctcnt></sdtsterm></ptvctinf></spdoinfo><spref><horizsys><geograph><latres>8.9831528411952133e-009</latres><longres>8.9831528411952133e-009</longres><geogunit>Decimal Degrees</geogunit></geograph><geodetic><horizdn>D North American 1983</horizdn><ellips>GRS 1980</ellips><semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis><denflat>298.257222101</denflat></geodetic></horizsys></spref><eainfo><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>CBRS_Polygons</enttypl></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>SHAPE_Area</attrlabl><attrdef>Area of feature in internal units squared.</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Unit</attrlabl><attrdef>Unique identifier for each individual CBRS unit.</attrdef><attrdefs>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Units designated in 1982 typically start with letters A (Maine), C (Massachusetts), D (Rhode Island), E (Connecticut), F (New York), H (Delaware), K (Virginia), L (North Carolina), M (South Carolina), N (Georgia), P (Florida), Q (Alabama), R (Mississippi), S (Louisiana), or T (Texas).  Units designated in 1990 typically start with the two letter state abbreviation.  The Unit Numbers for Otherwise Protected Areas end in “P”.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl><attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Unit_Type</attrlabl><attrdef>CBRS units are one of two types: “System Units” and “Otherwise Protected Areas”.</attrdef><attrdefs>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</attrdefs><attrdomv><edom><edomv>System Unit</edomv><edomvd>Most new Federal expenditures and financial assistance, including Federal flood insurance, are prohibited within System units.</edomvd></edom><edom><edomv>Otherwise Protected Area</edomv><edomvd>The only Federal spending prohibition within OPAs is the prohibition on Federal flood insurance.</edomvd></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Tier</attrlabl><attrdomv><edom><edomv>1</edomv><edomvd>Centerline Boundaries: Tier 1 accuracy level polygons were created by digitizing the center of the CBRS boundaries shown on the official paper maps.</edomvd></edom><edom><edomv>2</edomv><edomvd>Digital Conversion and Comprehensively Modernized Boundaries:  Polygons attributed with a Tier 2 accuracy level were created with modern Geographic Information Systems (GIS) technology using orthorectified aerial imagery (orthoimagery) as the base map.</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdef>The polygons in this data set have two tiers of horizontal accuracy depending on the methods used for digitization of the boundary lines, and the age and quality of the official CBRS map.  Tier 1 polygons are of lower quality and accuracy than Tier 2 polygons.  See the Horizontal Accuracy Statement for more information.</attrdef><attrdefs>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</attrdefs></attr></detailed><overview><eaover>CBRS Units:  The Coastal Barrier Resources Act (CBRA), as amended, established the John H. Chafee Coastal Barrier Resources System (CBRS), a defined set of geographic units along the Atlantic, Gulf of Mexico, Great Lakes, U.S. Virgin Islands, and Puerto Rico coasts.  Most new Federal expenditures and financial assistance are prohibited within the CBRS, unless those activities qualify for an exception under Section 6 of CBRA (16 U.S.C. § 3505).  The U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (Service), through the Secretary of the Interior, is responsible for administering CBRA which includes consulting with Federal agencies that propose spending funds within the CBRS.  There are two types of units within the CBRS; “System units” and “Otherwise Protected Areas” (OPAs).  The boundaries of System units are generally intended to follow geomorphic, development, or cultural features (e.g., wetland/upland interface, roads, etc.) and are depicted on the CBRS maps with bold solid lines.  Most new Federal expenditures and financial assistance, including Federal flood insurance, are prohibited within System units.   The CBRS currently includes 585 System units, which add up to approximately 1.3 million acres of land and associated aquatic habitat.  The boundaries of OPAs are generally intended to coincide with the boundaries of conservation or recreation areas such as state parks and national wildlife refuges.  OPAs are depicted on the CBRS maps with dotted/dashed lines and unit names followed by a “P” (e.g., FL-20P).  The only Federal spending prohibition within OPAs is the prohibition on Federal flood insurance.  The CBRS currently includes 272 OPAs which add up to approximately 1.8 million acres of land and associated aquatic habitat.</eaover></overview></eainfo><metainfo><metd>20121119</metd><metrd>20121117</metrd><metc><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</cntorg><cntper>Katie Niemi</cntper></cntorgp><cntpos>National Coastal Barriers Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>4401 N. Fairfax Drive, Suite 840</address><city>Arlington</city><state>Virginia</state><postal>22203</postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>703-358-2161</cntvoice><cntemail>CBRA@fws.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></metc><metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn><metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv><mettc>local time</mettc><metuc>No warranty, expressed or implied is made with regard to the accuracy of these data, and no liability is assumed by the U.S. Government in general, or the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, in specific as to the spatial or attribute accuracy of the data.  The act of distribution shall not constitute any such warranty, and no responsibility is assumed by the U.S. Government in the use of these files.  The boundary information in the CBRS polygons are for informational purposes only; their depiction and designation for informational purposes does not constitute a determination of jurisdictional authority or rights of ownership or entitlement and they are not survey grade or legal land descriptions.  Additionally, user must (1) read and fully comprehend the metadata prior to data use, (2) acknowledge the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service as the originator when using the data set as a source, and (3) share data products developed using this source data set with the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service.  Data should not be used beyond the limits of the source scale.  The data set is NOT to be used for definitive in/out CBRS determinations.</metuc></metainfo><Esri><CreaDate>20121120</CreaDate><CreaTime>12194300</CreaTime><ArcGISstyle>FGDC CSDGM Metadata</ArcGISstyle><SyncOnce>TRUE</SyncOnce><DataProperties><itemProps><itemLocation><linkage Sync="TRUE">http://www.fws.gov/CBRA/Maps/metadata.html</linkage></itemLocation></itemProps></DataProperties></Esri><distinfo><distliab>Although these data and information have been processed successfully on a computer system at the USFWS, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data and information on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data, and information, and aggregate use with other data and information. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data and information. The USFWS shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data and information described and/or contained herein.</distliab><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>Katie Niemi</cntper><cntorg>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</cntorg></cntperp><cntpos>National Coastal Barriers Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype><address>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</address><address>4401 N. Fairfax Drive, Suite 840</address><city>Arlington</city><state>VA</state><postal>22203</postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>703-358-2161</cntvoice><cntemail>CBRA@fws.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib><resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc></distinfo></metadata>
