<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Georgia DNR</origin>
        <title>TurtleNests_GA</title>
        <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The Georgia Department of Natural Resources (GADNR) has been monitoring sea turtle nests since the 1970's and authorizes and trains participants to survey the beach to locate sea turtle nests. They also relocate nests when necessary, protect nests with predator-proof screening, monitor nests during incubation, and inventory nests after they emerge to determine hatch success. Nest protection project participants include individuals that belong to beach front communities, conservation organizations, federal, state, or local agencies and universities. All nests are verified by the presence of eggs or hatching activity. Standardized ground surveys are conducted daily starting in May. Participants are required to collect data on all nests including the species of turtle that laid the nest, date laid, and other management information. Additional information can be found at http://www.seaturtle.org/nestdb/?view=3. All nests reported for this dataset were laid by loggerheads between 2006 and 2011. Nesting data is reported as mean annual density (nest count/km.) for each beach and spans the years 2006 to 2011. If there were two or more years, the coefficient of variance of the mean was also provided.</abstract>
      <purpose>This GIS dataset was created for the purpose of describing the mean nest densities of loggerhead sea turtles on Georgia beaches surveyed from 2006-2011 so that these biological resources can be considered for any planned energy development or other coastal use activity.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20060101</begdate>
          <enddate>20100101</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>Unknown</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>None planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-81.469108</westbc>
        <eastbc>-80.839997</eastbc>
        <northbc>32.029781</northbc>
        <southbc>30.713784</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>Loggerhead sea turtle</themekey>
        <themekey>Caretta caretta</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>Georgia</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>Neither the State of South Carolina, the State of Georgia, the SC and GA Department of Natural Resources, nor any of its employees, is responsible for any improper or incorrect use of the information described and/or contained herein, and assume no responsibility for the use of the information. The Georgia Department of Natural Resources should be acknowledged as the data source in products derived from these data. The South Carolina Department of Natural Resources should be acknowledged as the GIS data source in products derived from these data.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>Georgia Department of Natural Resources</cntorg>
          <cntper>Mark Dodd</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>physical</addrtype>
          <address>1 Conservation Way</address>
          <city>Brunswick</city>
          <state>GA</state>
          <postal>31520</postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>912-280-6892</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>Mark.Dodd@dnr.state.ga.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <native> Version 6.2 (Build 9200) ; Esri ArcGIS 10.1.0.3035</native>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Beach length accuracy is variable and dependent on the method used to measure the survey extent or beach length (GPS, odometer, etc).</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>a. Field process: Nest Counts: Nest count data were collected during daily ground surveys by trained and permitted volunteers, paid staff from conservation organizations, federal, state, or local agencies and universities. Most surveys were performed at sunrise when field signs are clearest. The extents of the surveys were noted by various methods (GPS, landmarks, odometers, etc). All nests were verified by the presence of eggs or signs of emergence at the end of incubation. Data from 2009, 2010 and 2011 were entered into an online database management system (http://www.seaturtle.org/nestdb/?view=3).</procdesc>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>GIS Process: The surveyed beach distanced was digitized from the 2010 USDA NAIP imagery using start and stop lat/longs.</procdesc>
        <proccont>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
              <cntorg>SCDNR</cntorg>
              <cntper>Jessica Boynton</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>GIS Manager I</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>physical</addrtype>
              <address>217 Fort Johnson Rd.</address>
              <city>Charleston</city>
              <state>SC</state>
              <postal>29412</postal>
              <country>US</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>843-953-9163</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>843-953-9820</cntfax>
            <cntemail>boyntonj@dnr.sc.gov</cntemail>
          </cntinfo>
        </proccont>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Vector</direct>
    <ptvctinf>
      <sdtsterm>
        <sdtstype>String</sdtstype>
        <ptvctcnt>13</ptvctcnt>
      </sdtsterm>
    </ptvctinf>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <mapproj>
          <mapprojn>Transverse Mercator</mapprojn>
          <transmer>
            <sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
            <longcm>-81.0</longcm>
            <latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
            <feast>500000.0</feast>
            <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
          </transmer>
        </mapproj>
        <planci>
          <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
          <coordrep>
            <absres>0.0001</absres>
            <ordres>0.0001</ordres>
          </coordrep>
          <plandu />
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>D North American 1983</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS 1980</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257222101</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>TurtleNests_GA</enttypl>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>OBJECTID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Location</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The description of the Georgia beaches surveyed.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>MeanNestDensity</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Mean nest density for each beach was calculated by summing all annual nest counts over the six years and dividing that by the total number of years (n = 6) to provide a mean nest count. The annual nest density (nests per kilometer) for each beach was calculated by dividing the mean nest count by the daily survey length in kilometers.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>N_Years</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Number of years surveyed.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CV</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Coefficient of variance of mean nest density.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Km</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The distance of beach surveyed.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape_Length</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Length of feature in internal units.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>South Carolina Department of Natural Resources</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntpos>Spatial Data Manager</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>P.O. Box 167 Rembert C. Dennis Building</address>
          <city>Columbia</city>
          <state>SC</state>
          <postal>29202</postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>803-734-9100</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>803-734-7001</cntfax>
        <cntemail>gisman@dnr.sc.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>See access and use constraints information.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>File Geodatabase Feature Class</formname>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt />
      </digform>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20130218</metd>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
    <mettc>local time</mettc>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>